Good morning everybody. We pick up today on דף ד. Daf Dalet.
Well, דף ד Daf Dalet is our דף. daf. We actually start
at the very bottom of ג עמוד ב, Gimmel Amud Bet, two
dots, three lines from the bottom. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So in
explaining the משנה, Mishna, we had dealt with a range of different
ways of reading who is הכל שוחטין. Hakol Shochtin. So and the
most interesting and the ones that we're going to be focusing on
are first of all two people whom you might not be able
to trust, which is the Samaritan and the person who doesn't care
about כשרות. kashrus. And then the question of even somebody you can
trust, what is the basic level of qualification that we care about?
Do they have to be tested to be an expert in knowledge?
Do they have to be known to have had experience? So now
we are going to go and look at these one by one.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So our Rabbis taught. שחיטת כותי מותרת. Shechitas
Kuti muteres.
The slaughtering of a Samaritan is permissible. במה דברים אמורים. Bameh devarim
amurim. When is this true? כשישראל עומד על גביו. kesheYisrael omeid al
gabav. If a Jew is directly standing on top of him. אבל
בא ומצאו ששחט, Aval bo u'metza'o sheshachat,
but if he was not directly observing and just found meat that
was slaughtered by this כותי, Kuti, חותך כזית ונותן לו. chotech kezayis
venosein lo. Then the way you test, again because they do know
the laws and they will do it for themselves but they might
not be doing it if they're going to be feeding it, you
know, giving it to other people, so you see if they're willing
to eat it itself.
אכלו, Achalo, if he eats it, מותר לאכול משחיטתו, mutar le'echol mishchitatos,
then you can eat from the שחיטה. shechita. ואם לאו, V'im lav,
and if he doesn't eat it, אסור לאכול משחיטתו, assur le'echol mishchitatos,
you cannot eat from the שחיטה. shechita. Okay, כיוצא בו, kayotzei bo,
similarly, מצא בידו דקוי של צפורים, matza beyado dikuy shel tzipporim,
if you find in his hand a basket or רש"י Rashi says
like a bundle, a bunch of birds,
what, dead birds, shechted birds, thank you. Can you just straighten that
camera? קוטר ראשו של אחד מהם ונותן לו. Koteir rosho shel echad
meihem venosein lo. So similarly you cut off the head of one
of them and you give it to him. אכלו מותר לאכול משחיטתו,
Achalo mutar le'echol mishchitatos, if he eats it you're allowed to eat
from his שחיטה. shechita. ואם לאו, V'im lav, and if not, אסור
לאכול משחיטתו, assur le'echol mishchitatos, you cannot. It seems like the exact
same case but the גמרא Gemara actually will think that the birds
example is a little more interesting. We'll see why in a minute.
So now we're going to revisit the debate of אביי Abaye and
רבא, Rava, whether you need direct supervision or popping in and out
is enough. So let's take a look. אביי דייק מרישא רבא דייק
מסיפא. Abaye dayik mei'reisha Rava dayik mei'seifa. So אביי Abaye infers his
position, דייק dayik means like to infer from a read of the
text, from a close, you know, from a close read of the
text. So אביי Abaye infers his position from the beginning of this
ברייתא Braisa and רבא Rava infers his position of popping in and
out from the end of the ברייתא. Braisa. אביי דייק מרישא. Abaye
dayik mei'reisha. אביי Abaye learned it out from the beginning of the
ברייתא. Braisa. טעמא דישראל עומד על גביו. Ta'ama deYisrael omeid al gabav.
The reason that it's okay is because a ישראל Yisrael is directly
standing over him. That's what the beginning of the ברייתא Braisa said.
If you are directly observing, directly standing over. אבל יוצא ונכנס לא,
Aval yotzei venichnas lo, anything less than that, even if it was
just popping in and out, no, you could not eat. So he
says, look, the beginning says when can you eat from the שחיטה
shechita of a כותי? Kuti? If you are directly observing, which means
any lesser form of supervision, even going in and out, would not
suffice. So אביי Abaye says it's very clear from the רישא reisha
you need direct supervision. רבא דייק מסיפא. Rava dayik mei'seifa. רבא Rava
looks at the end of the ברייתא. Braisa. טעמא דבא ומצאו ששחט.
Ta'ama deba u'metza'o sheshachat.
The end of the ברייתא Braisa says what's the case that you
have to do the test of feeding him, that you can't trust
it? Is you came and you found that he had already slaughtered.
Which means that only when it's already slaughtered is it no good.
Anything better than that, any supervision better than that would be okay.
אבל יוצא ונכנס שפיר דמי, Aval yotzei venichnas shapir dami, anything better
than no supervision would be okay, which is the popping in and
out, would be okay. Thank you very much. So what this is,
and this is what I believe Aristotle calls the excluded middle. The
excluded middle meaning that the opposite of A is not B, the
opposite of A is not A. The opposite of chocolate is not
vanilla, the opposite of chocolate is not chocolate. So
we normally describe things that are both extremes and we can often
leave out, well what about the middle case? And the גמרא Gemara
always wants to figure out what about the middle case. So that's
exactly the problem here in this ברייתא. Braisa. It says if you're
directly standing over it's okay, but if there was no supervision then
you need to give him the piece of meat. Well there's a
case between direct supervision and no supervision, which is the case of
יוצא ונכנס, yotzei venichnas, popping in and out. So אביי Abaye thinks
that anything less than the first case of direct supervision is no
good. Anything רבא Rava thinks anything better than the last case, anything
better than no supervision is okay, which is the popping in and
out. So that's how they get their different positions from the ambiguity
of the ברייתא. Braisa. So let's take a look at now what
the גמרא Gemara says.
The ambiguity is that
it talks about
what's ambiguous about it.
It leaves out the middle case. It excluded middle says if you
were directly supervising it's okay, if you found the כותי Kuti had
already slaughtered the meat then it's not okay you have to, you
have to feed him the meat to see if it's okay.
In case the heads aren't cut off?
Our case is,
what's ambiguous about this case?
What's no, the
case that's not
addressed is what is... What about periodic supervision? That's what's not addressed
and that אביי Abaye and רבא Rava have different positions based on.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ולאביי קשיא סיפא. ul'Abaye kasha seifa.
So אביי, Abaye,
how does he explain the end of the ברייתא brayta that says
no supervision is a problem? That makes it sound like minimal supervision
is okay. So אמר לך, amar lach, he would say to you:
no, יוצא ונכנס נמי בו מצאו קרא ליה. yotzei v'nichnas nami bo
matzo kare lei. If all that you were doing was popping in
and out, that's basically no supervision. That's like you came and you
found that it had already been shechted. So he says, yeah, the
reason it's not addressing the case of popping in and out is
because that is effectively the same as not supervising at all. And
that's when the end of the ברייתא brayta says no supervision, you
have to feed it to him, includes the case of יוצא ונכנס.
yotzei v'nichnas. Okay, ולרבא קשיא רישא. ul'Rava kasha reisha. So how about
רבא, Rava, what does he do with the beginning that says direct
supervision counts? So it sounds like only direct supervision. So רבא Rava
will say the same in the reverse, אמר לך, amar lach, he'll
tell you יוצא ונכנס נמי כעומד על גביו דמי. yotzei v'nichnas nami
k'omed al gabav dami. No,
popping in and out, that's equivalent to direct supervision. So when the
ברייתא brayta says you need to be directly supervising, it means and
anything that counts as direct supervision including popping in and out. So
basically we're back to the fact that the ברייתא brayta explains the
two extremes: direct supervision, no supervision. It doesn't tell you what the
הלכה halacha is about the middle case, and each about sort of
this popping in and out, and each one will interpret it through
their own lens. אביי Abaye will say, 'oh, it didn't have to
tell you that because that's obviously equivalent to no supervision.' רבא Rava
will say, 'it didn't have to tell you that because that's obviously
the same as direct supervision.' So that's what happens when you don't
address the middle case, you leave it open for debate and interpretation.
Rachel?
Does the parallel
of these principles also apply to the משגיח? mashgiach?
Well yeah, that came up yesterday and generally the answer is yes,
although as we saw the גמרא Gemara itself said that אביי Abaye
would admit, agree that in certain cases popping in and out is
okay, like we say by יין נסך. yayin nesech. To make sure
that the non-Jew or the non-Jewish worker isn't touching your wine, so
your popping in and out of the store there is okay. Here
he requires more direct supervision because he's already handling the meat and
he could get away with more and therefore he needs more. So
yes, those are the two models: direct supervision and popping in and
out, and which one you need is to some degree sort of
context-specific and circumstance-specific. So yes it is relevant to the issues of
השגחה, hashgacha, but there's not a direct mapping to some degree. For
example, we base, our, what we basically do in the world of
supervision of restaurants is we say dairy restaurants you can have יוצא
ונכנס, yotzei v'nichnas, popping in and out, פליישיג fleishig restaurants you need
a משגיח תמידי. mashgiach temidi. Now it's nowhere in the גמרא Gemara
that it says that. There's no, but based on what are the
levels of concerns and the possibility that something will go wrong either
unintentionally or intentionally,
there's much greater concerns in the case of a פליישיג fleishig restaurant
than a מילכיג milchig restaurant and that's how we sort of split
it. But it's not because there's like a direct line in the
גמרא Gemara that says that, because these are the two models and
we use them, apply them based on what are the circumstances and
the concerns. I'm sorry, yes?
Just the parallel because we're concerned that things can go wrong here.
Exactly, and how much either intentional or
unintentional error, possible errors, do you have to, are you concerned about,
and which would determine how much direct supervision is needed. Yes.
So in this dispute between רבא Rava and אביי, Abaye, usually הלכה
halacha is according to רבא. Rava. Right. So this isn't,
this isn't one of the exceptions.
Correct. I mean, I have to check but I think that we
actually פסקן pasken like רבא Rava here. Is that a question or
is that a statement?
Well that was, that was a question followed up on what Rachel
said, that seemed to imply that we might well be able to
be lenient on...
Yeah, I'd have to look because I've not seen here a פסק
psak and really is only by the, this is, I'd have to
check because we don't פסקן pasken in cases of כותים kutim nowadays,
not because they don't exist, well actually even up through, yeah, there
is a Samaritan community, it's actually a sad story because, I mean
whatever, there's even like a משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah that talks at
one place about Samaritans and I thought that that was like a,
I thought he was just talking about reform Jews and trying to
sort of be nice about it or something, but actually there was
a, I mean now there are a few, but there was a
strong Samaritan
community up, even in Eastern Europe. There's actually, I don't know if
people are aware, during the Holocaust they managed to convince the Germans
that they were not Jews and they actually were saved the fate
of the Holocaust. And a lot
of rabbinic, oh no, is that the Samaritan?
נטורי קרתא, Neturei Karta, if you're thinking Karait...
I'm sorry, I'm thinking Karaites, not Samaritans. I'm sorry,
I'm confusing it. I'm thinking Karaites. Yeah, that was the story with
the Karaites. And then there's the story was that a lot
of
non-Karaites...
So
anyway, they're about a thousand in Israel.
There are a thousand Samaritans? Okay, but besides that there are not
so many Samaritans, the reason we don't have פסק psak so much
about Samaritans is because the גמרא Gemara says if you remember there
was a debate about whether they're considered Jewish or not Jewish, the
גמרא Gemara says that even those that consider them Jewish at a
certain point it's they had all turned to idolatry and they were
basically given the status of non-Jews anyway. So there's not really too
much פסק paskened הלכה halacha about Samaritans. So this issue about popping
in and out is not would not occur in a case of
a כותי, Kuti, so what type of a person would you be
afraid is going to ruin the שחיטה, shechita, a Jew that you
have to pop in and out? Maybe the guy of the case
of the מומר, mumar, but we'll see he has different standards. So
I don't know how whether this is פסק paskened or not, but
it's a good question, I can check how he פסק. paskens. Okay,
so this is the debate about whether it's direct supervision or popping
in and out by the כותי. Kuti. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, let's continue. כיוצא בו, kiyotzei bo,
so the ברייתא baraita continues in a similar fashion, מצא בידו דיקוריה
של צפורים, matza beyado dikkurya shel tzipparim,
if you find either a basket or a bundle of birds, קוטר
ראשו של אחד, koteir rosho shel echad, so you take the head
and you see if he'll eat it. אמאי Ammai? the גמרא Gemara
says why does that work? If we're talking about a bundle, ליחוש
דלמא האי הוא דהוי שחיט שפיר. leichush dilma hai hu dehavi shachit
shapir.
Maybe some he slaughtered good because he was slaughtering them for himself
and others he didn't bother to slaughter well and the one you
fed him he happens to know was one of the ones that
he slaughtered well. Correct. All right, thank you Michael that'll be the
answer. But anyway, how can you trust that everything was done correctly
just cause he was willing to eat one? Now you could have
answered before you get to Michael's answer with the גמרא, Gemara, what
is the likelihood, you know, that you're going to do a few
correctly and a few incorrectly? Either you're planning on, you know, eating
them for yourself or your family or whatever you're going to do
them all incorrectly or you're not going to bother with any but
the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. The גמרא Gemara is actually concerned
maybe he intends to do it for spite? Maybe he intends to
give some to...
Right, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara concerned with. So why is
it enough that he eats one? So אמר רב מנשיא Amar Rav
Menasha so רב מנשיא Rav Menasha says במכניסם, bemachnisam, giving the parenthesis,
במכניסם תחת כנפיו. bemachnisam tachat kenafav.
You hide all the birds under your under your coat, under your
under your cloak, under your wing. You pull out one head and
you feed it to him. He doesn't know which head it is.
So if he'll eat that, you know they're all good. So the
גמרא Gemara says what?
Why the head?
I have no idea.
Why does he take home the rest of the...
Presumably because right you don't want to eat he wants to save
the rest of it. Exactly.
Or maybe he just...
Ah,
so the גמרא's Gemara going to ask that. ודלמא סימנא הוה יהיב
ליה בגוויה. Vidilma simana hava yaiv leh begaveh.
Maybe since maybe if he slaughtered some correctly some incorrectly, maybe he
made for himself a little mark which was the good one which
was the not good one? So maybe he sees the mark and
he knows that it's okay. So you still can't infer to the
rest. So אמר רב משרשיא, Amar Rav Mesharshaya, רב משרשיא Rav Mesharshaya
says דממסמס ליה ממוסמי, demimasmas leh mimusmei,
that you sort of mush it up. That's a very technical term.
So you take one of the heads, he doesn't see which one
you're taking, you smush it up, you make it into ground meat
so if he made any mark he couldn't see, and then you
feed it to him. Now if he doesn't want to eat it
might have more to do than just כשרות kashrus but okay anyway
and only then. So the גמרא Gemara says now the גמרא Gemara
now the גמרא Gemara turns itself from this question about jumping from
one to the other to the core question about to what degree
do we think that כותים, Kutim, right our basic concern is do
they care about other people's eating non-kosher food? But the assumption is
if they're doing it for themselves they're doing it correctly. And now
the גמרא's Gemara going to question that. How do we know that
even if they're doing it for themselves they really keep by all
the laws of שחיטה shechita and will do it correctly? Right, cause
we're going to assume if he's willing to eat it we know
he did the right job, our only concern is he might be
not caring about us. So now we're going to ask how do
we know their laws are the same as our laws and they
really are careful about their own observance even for themselves? Yes, Rachel.
I'm a little bothered by the tone of all of this. And
I don't understand the subtext.
Why would we have any reason
to
doubt... I mean this what we're really saying is that this person
is so dubious that he may really go out of his way
to purposely give us something that we shouldn't use yet we want
to trust his שחיטה? shechita? If he feels this way about someone
we shouldn't trust their שחיטה shechita but when somebody starts to go
through all this kind of reasoning it's more of a reflection on
the rabbis than on the כותי.
Kutite. Well, okay, yes, but what I would say is there clearly
was strong antagonism between the כותים Kutim and the Jews when they
came I believe if I'm remembering my someone can correct me if
I'm remembering
my עזרא נחמיה Ezra Nechemia correctly that when they came to rebuild
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash the Samaritans actually were opposed it at
the time the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. and really tried to prevent
it from happening. So there was a lot of ongoing conflict
and the Rabbis because they were concerned about, you know, about general
issues about observance actually had some very harsh rulings against כותים. Kutim.
So there seemed to have been, without trying to figure out who
started it and who's to blame, there was definitely ongoing antagonism between
the two groups. Okay, so I think because of that, you know,
they're assuming here that maybe they'll be firm for themselves, but not
care, maybe either just not care or even maybe intentionally try to
mess us up because of this antagonism. So again, you could say,
well, maybe we're to blame for the antagonism and maybe when we
make these types of rulings we feed into it. That might be,
I'm not a historian and I'm not in position to judge that,
but there was that reality of, you know, of that ongoing antagonism
between the כותים Kutim and the Jews.
So would you trust somebody to do our שחיטה shechitah that we
think has limited...
Right, so that is what is amazing...
right, I'd say if they have high enough cognitive capacity for distortion...
Yes, so what I would say is, meaning I would take the
positive message away from here, not the negative. Not like, oh, look
how terrible this is that we're distrusting them. I think that it
was based on some reality without trying to figure out who was
to blame. I would take away the positive message. Here you have
a גמרא Gemara that's taking somebody that basically follows an entire different
system of הלכה halacha because they're not turning to the Rabbis for
פסק, psak, they're going to their own traditions and sometimes there's overlap
and sometimes there's not, and even so we're willing to consider that
we might be able to eat from the שחיטה. shechitah. Or the
other case we're going to get to is the מומר אוכל נבילות,
mumar ochel neveilos, the person who basically doesn't care about כשרות, kashrut,
okay? He's willing to eat טריפה. treif. And there as well, we're
trying, we're going to argue that in certain circumstances we can trust
that person's שחיטה. shechitah. So if anything, I would say the message
is look how sort of liberal-minded the Rabbis were, you know, and
that they were not categorically excluding people just because, oh, you don't
go to Rabbis for your פסק, psak, you go to your Samaritan
authorities. Oh, you don't keep כשר, kosher, so we can absolutely never
trust you. They were willing to consider the possibility that under certain
circumstances it could be trusted. So I think that's what's surprising in
the opposite direction, not the exclusion, but the inclusion, given how the
reality is being perceived. Okay, so let's take a look now at
how the גמרא Gemara continues. So it says like this: ודילמא קסברי
כותים אין שחיטה לעוף מן התורה. Vedilma kasavri Kutim ein shechitah le'of
min HaTorah. Maybe the Samaritans think that there's no such thing as
halachic slaughtering of birds. Why specifically birds? Because when the תורה Torah
talks about large animals, mammals, it says וזבחת, vezavachta,
you shall slaughter. Now, it never tells you that there are הלכות
halachot about slaughter, but at least it refers to the act of
slaughter. It never says this about birds. It never uses the verb
וזבחת vezavachta or ושחטת, veshachata, which is not a verb in the
תורה, Torah, whatever, anyway, well it does לשחוט את בנו... lishchot et
beno...
ושחט את בן הבקר...
veshachat et
ben habakar... yes, how does it say, ושחטת... veshachata... anyway, it never
says any of those verbs by birds. So there's a general assumption
that maybe by a somewhat analogy of Samaritans to Karaites, like I
accidentally did before, that Samaritans are better about things that are in
the written תורה. Torah. Especially because if they have different authorities, you
know, there's a lot more that's up for grabs when it comes
to oral traditions than written. So therefore, it's saying, look, if birds
are not written in the תורה Torah שחיטה, shechitah, how can we
trust their שחיטה shechitah by birds? Maybe even for themselves they don't
believe that there's any laws of שחיטה shechitah by birds. Okay, so
that's the question. So let's see what it says: אין שחיטה לעוף
מן התורה. Ein shechitah le'of min HaTorah. So the גמרא Gemara says:
אבוך וטעמך, Aboch veta'amech, according to you, that you're concerned about things
that are not written, that maybe they don't abide by them even
for themselves, שהייה דרסה חלדה הגרמה ועיקור, shehiyah, drasah, chaladah, hagramah, ve'ikkur,
מי כתיבן? mi ketivan? These other five major concerns about how a
שחיטה shechitah can be done improperly. Let's talk about what they are.
שהייה Shehiyah is pausing,
which is exactly what it sounds like, in the middle of the
שחיטה shechitah you stop and you pause before you've completed the swipe.
דריסה, drisah, דרסה drasah is when you apply pressure rather than letting
the sharpness of the knife do the cutting. חלדה Chaladah is tunneling,
I guess would be how it's explained, which is you stick the
knife between the trachea and the esophagus rather than cutting the trachea
and the esophagus from the outside, you know, and you start outside
and you cut them both, you start in the middle and you
either cut them singly... tunneling... well no, you actually slice them correctly,
but you start between the two rather than starting here and cutting
down, you start between the two and you cut them both, you
cut them like that, okay? That would be
דרסה... drasah... I'm sorry... no, I'm sorry, הגרמה hagramah is slaughtering it
too high or too low along the, you know, along the neck,
along the throat. And עיקור ikkur is uprooted, which basically means tearing
out one of the סימנים, simanim, either the trachea or the esophagus
before cutting it. So we'll see specifics about that later. Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says: Okay, but even if it says שחיטה shechitah in
the תורה, Torah, it never tells you any of the details. So
if you're afraid that Samaritans don't keep laws that are not explicit
None, none of the laws of שחיטה Shechita are explicit. So how
could we ever trust them even if they're doing it for themselves?
So מי כתיבא? mi ksiva? אלא, ella, what must you say? כיון
דאחזיקי בהו אחזיקי. keivan de achziki behu achziki. Since it's something they've
embraced, they've embraced it. Now I should say רש״י Rashi reads the
word אחזיקו achziku in different ways here. Sometimes he reads the words
in this context to be embraced, they've embraced it, and sometimes he
reads it that we have a חזקה chazaka vis-à-vis them. We can
assume we that they are doing it correctly. And that's certainly at
least the the way we have it in our text, it sounds
so much here, it mostly sounds like it's referring to their practice.
So I'm going to read it that way. So what do we
say? We say: is it a practice that they've adopted? They've adopted
it, whether it's written or not written. So הכא נמי hacha nami
here too by birds, let's say: כיון דאחזיקו אחזיקו. keivan de achziku
achziku. Since they've embraced it, they've embraced it. So meaning: who cares
whether it's written or not written? We can believe that there are
certain things that Samaritans do, and at least for themselves they do
correctly with all of the details that the rabbis have said. There
are some things like that whether it's written or not. So now
the גמרא Gemara is going to explore that question: what are the
different parameters in which we can assume things that the Samaritans keep
or don't keep? So let's take a look. ואחזוק ולא אחזוק, v'achzuk
v'lo achzuk, things that they, whether they have embraced something or not
embraced
something בלא כתיבא b'lo ksiva regarding a matter that's not written in
the תורה, Torah, תנאי היא. tannai hi. This is, we're going to
say, is a debate of תנאי tannai whether, what status we give
something that is not written in the תורה Torah that they have
embraced. Whether we consider it to be something that we can rely
on them for. דתניא, detanya, now let's take a look. Okay, and
this becomes, this is a famous ברייתא braita about different opinions about
trusting the whether Samaritans are doing it correctly. Let's take a look.
מצת כותי, matzas kuti, you have מצה matza made by a Samaritan.
So there are two questions: one is can you make sure it's
not חמץ? chametz? And the other question is: can you eat it
for the first night of פסח Pesach and to do your מצוה
mitzvah of מצה? matza? So what's the story? מותרת, mutteres, number one
it's מותר. mutter. You can assume it's not חמץ. chametz. ואדם יוצא
בה ידי חובתו בפסח v'adam yotzei bah yedei chovaso b'Pesach and you
can use it for your first night of פסח. Pesach. The difference
is is that it's one thing not to be חמץ, chametz, but
in order to use it for the first night, you have to
have שימור. shimur. You have to have an act of watching it
and making sure it doesn't become חמץ. chametz. It's not just the
reality that it's not חמץ, chametz, but it needs שימור. shimur. It
might even need שימור לשם מצה shimur l'shem matza for the sake
of the מצוה. mitzvah. That's a whole different debate about what type,
what constitutes שמורה מצה shmura matza essentially for the סדר Seder night.
But the first opinion is you can trust it for both purposes.
Okay. רבי אליעזר
אוסר, Rabbi Eliezer oser,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says: No, they are not careful with the
details. And the way רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is interpreted is: even
something that we know they keep, we can never know for sure
that they keep it with the same level of details and with
the same degree of scrupulousness as we would keep the law. Okay.
So he basically says you can't trust them for anything, even if
they're doing it for themselves. Because A: they don't work within our
system, so we don't know if they buy into all of the
details. And number two is: even if they do, we can't be
assured that they're actually scrupulous and careful about all the details. So
he says basically, you know, what Rachel was saying, which would be
I think our most normal assumption: Hey, if they're not part of
our system, who, you know, we don't have a control of this,
we don't have a handle on this, we can't trust anything. So
that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. Okay, now there's a third
opinion. כישראל, k'Yisrael, they're not as good as as Jews even in
knowing or in observing all of the details. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says: כל מצוה שהחזיקו בה כותים הרבה מדקדקין בה יותר
מישראל. kol mitzvah she'hecheziku bah Kutim harbeh medakdekin bah yoser mi'Yisrael. No,
wow!
If it's a מצוה mitzvah that they are careful about, they're even
פרומער frummer than Jews about it. So if you've identified one,
it means that they have their own religion, religious beliefs, and there's
some things... Why is that such a surprise? Some things that they
can be super פרום frum about. They don't keep everything we keep,
they have their own different system. But where there are areas of
overlap, they can be super פרום frum about it. Why don't you
accept believe that that phenomenon could exist?
Maybe they're saying negative about the Jews. That could be too.
What do you want to say, Seth?
No, I was just going to say that, you know, when I
think about the friends who aren't Jewish and they they would be
they'd sort of be like: You're not more scrupulous about this? They
take things very literally.
I I had a Reform Jewish friend who was absolutely stunned when
she heard that most most Orthodox Jews sell חמץ chametz rather than
getting rid of it.
There you go, right.
What's the word הרבה? harbeh? Yeah, what?
אדר, adar, the same?
No, I think it just means a lot. I think I read
הרבה harbeh as מאוד, meod, meaning מדקדקין בו הרבה, medakdekin bo harbeh,
you know, that's the way I read it.
הרבה מדקדקין בו,
harbeh medakdekin bo, they are, they are increasingly מדקדק, medakdek, excessively מדקדק,
medakdek, יותר מישראל. yoser mi'Yisrael. No, it says יותר כותים. yoser Kutim.
No,
I never read it that way. I always read הרבה מדקדקין. harbeh
medakdekin. No, I always read it as a modifier for מדקדקין. medakdekin.
They are excessively מדקדק, medakdek, more than ישראל, Yisrael, yes.
The middle פסוק? pasuk?
I suppose you could read it שהחזיקו בו. she'hecheziku bo. No. Okay,
that's how I read it. I'd be interested to see how different
English translations do.
The middle position is missing here. There's no תנא Tanna brought down
here who says well you can eat it but not for the
סדר. Seder.
Right, that's true. See we assume one of it's either all or
nothing. What does the ארטסקול Artscroll say there about הרבה מדקדקין? Harbe
Medakdekin? Does it say they are excessively scrupulous?
"Far more meticulous."
Far more meticulous. הרבה מדקדקין, Harbe Medakdekin, though. No, well, yeah, but
I think they're reading הרבה Harbe as just excessively or far more,
yes.
The things that could go wrong with שחיטה, Shechitah, didn't we have
that like a page or two beforehand? Yes.
ושחיטה וצליה וחתיכה, Ve-shechitah Ve-tzliyah Ve-chatichah, what they could have done wrong.
Yes.
But it's not the same.
Yeah, there we only mention three, here we're mentioning five. It was
an abbreviated list. I don't think there's any particular reason. Okay, so
anyway here's the debate. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to
try to understand what are, what are the parameters of this debate.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, so let's go back and look at it.
מצת כותי, Matzat Kuti, the מצה Matzah of a כותי, Kuti, מותרת,
Muteret, is permissible. ואדם יוצא בה ידי חובתו בפסח, Ve-adam Yotze Bah
Yedei Chovato Be-Pesach, and you can fulfill your מצוה. Mitzvah. So now
it's going to first focus on the point that Charlie said. פשיטא,
Pshita, obviously, once it's not חמץ, Chametz, of course you can use
it! So the גמרא Gemara says no, it's not so obvious. מהו
דתימא, Mahu De-teima, I might have thought לא בקיאי בשימור, Lo Beki'ei
Be-shimur, they might be good at making sure that it's, you know,
it might be that it's not חמץ, Chametz, but on the other
hand they don't watch it in the type of special watching that
is required to make it legitimate for פסח Pesach for the סדר
Seder night, which we're not going to discuss right now. קמשמע לן
Kamashma Lan that that they also care about, not just that it's
not חמץ, Chametz, but they actually do specially watch it for that
sake and it can be used סדר Seder night, if we assume
it's something that they do and they care about. רבי אליעזר אוסר,
Rabbi Eliezer Oser, now we're going to look at רבי אליעזר's Rabbi
Eliezer opinion. לפי שאין בקיאין בדקדוקי מצות, Lefi She-ein Beki'in Be-dikdukei Mitzvot,
they don't, we can never trust them, even if it's something that
they do, we can't trust them to be scrupulous about the details.
קסבר, Kasavar, he holds לא בקיאי בשימור. Lo Beki'ei Be-shimur. They are
not expert regarding the issue about watching. Now there's two points. Number
one, רש"י Rashi points out that the word שימור Shimur here does
not mean what it meant a second ago, because the second ago
it meant to use it for the סדר Seder night, and here
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying you can't even eat it anytime
on פסח. Pesach. Because when it says אסר, Asar, he forbade, it
doesn't just mean for the סדר Seder night, but it means he's
considered that it's חמץ. Chametz. So here it means that they're not
careful about even preventing it from becoming חמץ. Chametz. The other problem
is, is that the phrasing is imprecise. Because it should not have
said לא בקיאי. Lo Beki'ei. That makes it sound like according to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer there will be some things that they do
know and do care about and we could trust them. And רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer whole point is no matter what they keep, you
can never assume they do it with the right degree of care
and scrupulousness. So this phrasing here is a little imprecise, but in
other cases it's clear that the גמרא Gemara interprets רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer like the simple read of his words, which is that no
matter what they're keeping, you can never assume they're doing it to
our standard. Okay, so. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel,
now we're going to the more interesting issue which is רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel and the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כל מצוה שהחזיקו בה כותים הרבה מדקדקין
בה יותר מישראל. Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel Omer Kol Mitzvah She-hechziku Bah
Kutim Harbe Medakdekin Bah Yoter Mi-Yisrael. Anything they do, they are much
more scrupulous. היינו תנא קמא, Hainu Tanna Kamma, so the גמרא Gemara
says effectively, although the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma didn't say they're more
scrupulous, but who cares? Effectively it's the same as the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. They both say you can trust the כותים Kutim for
the issue of the מצה. Matzah. So what's the difference? לכתחילה? Le-chatchilah?
So wait a minute. No, and there's no, there's no איכא בינייהו
Ika Beineihu here, I mean I understand, but there's no indication. But
he says you can use it for סדר Seder night. So איכא
בינייהו דכתיבא ולא אחזיקו בה. Ika Beineihu De-chtivah Ve-lo Achziku Bah. Ah,
let's try to say this is the difference. Now it's obviously reading
something into the ברייתא Braita that isn't here, but רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel emphasizes anything they are מוחזקין Mouchzakin in,
anything we know that they've embraced. So for him, before I'm going
to trust a כותי, Kuti, I have to know that this is
a particular area of הלכה Halachah that they have embraced. The תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma never said that I know that they've embraced it.
So how would the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma assume that you can
trust them by מצה Matzah if we don't, if he never said
because they've embraced it? So it must be what the גמרא Gemara
is going to read in is, is well, maybe because מצה Matzah
is written in the תורה. Torah. And therefore we can assume that
anything written they're careful about. So the גמרא Gemara constructs this as
their debate, obviously the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma never mentioned the fact
that it was written, but they're trying to understand what are the
differences. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel emphasizes that
they, we know they've embraced it and therefore maybe for the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma what's important is that it's written. Wait a minute,
let's just finish this. תנא קמא סבר, Tanna Kamma Savar, so איכא
בינייהו דכתיבא ולא אחזיקו בה. Ika Beineihu De-chtivah Ve-lo Achziku Bah. The
difference would be something that's written and we don't know that they've
embraced it. We don't know that, so that they observe it. תנא
קמא סבר, Tanna Kamma Savar, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds, כיון
דכתיבא, Keivan De-chtivah, if it's written, אף על גב דלא אחזיקו בה,
Af Al Gav De-lo Achziku Bah, even if we don't know, meaning
not that we know they haven't but we don't know that they've
embraced, therefore we can trust them and therefore he didn't mention that
they embraced it by מצה. Matzah. As long as it's written, we
know that they'll keep it, or we'll assume they'll keep it. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל סבר, Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel Savar, and רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel holds, אי אחזיקו
אין, Ei Achziku Ein, only if something that they embraced, אי לא
אחזיקו לא, Ei Lo Achziku Lo, if it's something they haven't embraced,
no, and that's why he said no, if they've embraced it, then
we can trust it. So, so the גמרא Gemara says no, אי
הכי, Ei Hachi, if that's true, that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon Ben Gamliel is coming to sort of limit the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, say you can't just rely on the fact that it's
written, you have to know they embraced it. So כל מצוה שהחזיקו
בה כותים, Kol Mitzvah She-hechziku Bah Kutim, it shouldn't say any מצוה
Mitzvah the כותים Kutim embraced, which sounds like he's coming to expand
the, the category, he should have used the phrasing אם יחזיקו מיבעי
ליה, Im Yachziku Miba'ei Lei, if they embraced, meaning saying to the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, you say
it's enough that it's
written, no, it's... broaden it. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
just nuance it a little bit. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אלא איכא בינייהו, Ella ika beinaihu, so you're right. Let's
focus on a different difference. Not that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel is limiting the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, but the
reverse. דלא כתיבא, Delo ketiva, something that is not written, ואחזיקו בה.
ve'achziku bah. Meaning before we said it was written and we don't
know they have a חזקה. chazakah. This is the flip. Something is
not written in the תורה Torah but we know they have embraced.
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma סבר savar כיון דלא כתיבא אף על גב
דאחזיקו בה נמי לא. keivan delo ketiva af al gav de'achziku bah
nami lo. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds even if I know
they embraced it, for me what's important is only things that are
written. We can trust them on things that they happen to have
embraced that is not written, can't trust them on. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel סבר savar and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, כיון דאחזוק אחזוק. keivan de'achzuk achzuk.
As long as they've embraced it, they've embraced it. So in the
end it's sort of what we said before except emphasizing the other
part of their debate. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says for me
what the things I can trust them on are things that are
written in the תורה. Torah. I don't care if I know that
they've embraced it, I don't know they've embraced it. I'm going to
assume things written in the תורה Torah are things that they keep.
Okay? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, it
has nothing to do with whether it's written in the תורה. Torah.
It has to do with things that I know that they've embraced
or not embraced. So even if it's written in the תורה, Torah,
if they haven't embraced it, we can't trust them. And if it's
not written in the תורה, Torah, if I know they have embraced
it, we can trust them. So the גמרא Gemara therefore sets this
up as the debate: Do you go by written or embraced? And
the way this ties back is the question about the birds. Birds
are not written. So can we trust them? So according to רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, if we know they've embraced
the principle of שחיטה shechitah by birds, we could trust them. According
to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, no, if it's not written in
the תורה, Torah, even if I know they've embraced this, I can't.
Now, the obvious question here is what sense is there in the
תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? Meaning once I'm prepared to trust them, you
know, it's not רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says I'll never assume they
have my standards. Okay, once I'm prepared to trust them, doesn't רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel make the most sense? I
mean, it's based on, you know, on empirical evidence of which are
the things that they're doing and not doing. Why would you reject
that and use the standard of what's written? So I don't have
a great answer, but what I will say is in my mind
what this reflects is the desire of הלכה halakhah to not have
to, you know, to have clear rules and not have to assess
every single case based on, you know, based on
fact-finding. So therefore, you know, if you say well, they do embrace
and they don't embrace, you know, that could change from location to
location, from this generation to the next generation. Maybe your fact-finding wasn't
good. You know, you did a random sample of the five people
that keep שחיטה, shechitah, but there are ten, but there's more that
don't. So it's much easier if we have rules. Now, the rules
are going to lead to a certain degree of, you know, out
of sync with the facts at all times, but at least they
are a better, you know, better way of doing law is by
having clear rules. So therefore, the assumption is that as I said
before, at least if it's written, there's an assumption that that is
something that, you know, they probably looked and they saw by and
large the Samaritans do things that are in the written תורה. Torah.
The real debates are things that are not in the written תורה.
Torah. So we're going to use that as our rule because that's
generally the case that things that are written they do and things
that are not written they don't do. And at least that's a
simple rule to follow even though, you know, the feeling you might
have is it's not as accurate as the position of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So that's what I think is
going on here. Charlie, yes?
But a lot of things
in הלכה, halakhah,
specifically כשרות, kashrut, are based on fact-finding. We have to determine a
lot of facts to determine whether we eat something.
Yeah, that's a good point.
And you know, I would assume though if you wanted to apply
that here, it would not be enough to say that I know
the כותים kutim are אחזיקו בה. achziku bah. I would have to
know by this particular guy. Right? If you imagine, for example, how
would this—by analogy—it says well, I tend to know that most people,
plants that make maple syrup do the following so I can assume
the same is true here. That's not the fact-finding we do. We
want to know what is the very specific facts about this particular
case, right? So nobody is saying that. Nobody's saying you have to
know this particular Samaritan.
And yet כשרות kashrut agencies do say something like that for maple
syrup.
Right. Right. Yeah, it's a very good point. It's a very good
point. You know,
so I don't know what to say. You're right. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel does make more sense. But there are
times where we just, you know, do things which are simpler and
more quantifiable than trying to always, you know, assess the facts in
any given case. So it's a good question. I'm doing the best
I can with the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Okay.
And I know that, you know, we kind of glossed over it,
but I really think that at least based on the implication of
what they're saying is according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel who says that if they really, you know, we know
they do it, they do it even better than we do, then
I would think that a possible thing would be לכתחילה, lechatkhilah, right?
In other words—so all this is לכתחילה. lechatkhilah.
No, no, no, meaning like if I have the choice between going
to a Jew, yeah, or going to a כותי kuti for
Yeah,
but you never see any of the cases here that it's a
בדיעבד bedieved for those that say it's good, if it says מצת
כותי מותרת matzat Kuti muteret אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח. adam
yotze bo yedei chovato b'Pesach. There's no hint here that that's בדיעבד.
bedieved.
No, right, no, but I'm saying you're saying what רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel would say is even if
it's לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Right, it could be, it could be according to
רבן
שמעון
בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon
ben
Gamliel, that might be true. Is that idea in the גמרא Gemara
at all though?
That there's a לכתחילה l'chatchila according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel? I don't know. Right, I don't know, but I'm
not sure he would take his the logic to that to that
extreme.
One other point though. You know, I don't know if any of
this has implications let's say for a Muslim who, you know, let's
say keeps halal or whatever it is. And let's say he wants
to do kosher for us. You know what I mean? Like he's
already in the פרשה parsha so to speak.
Well, the problem is non-Jews are categorically excluded and we'll get to
it, which is why some of these interesting things come up by
כותים, Kutim, which are technically Jews, but follow different systems. You know,
the more interesting question would be let's say a non-observant Jew, a
non-Orthodox Jew, which is things we'll get to also when we get
to the מומר mumar and סומר. somer. Yeah. Okay,
was there any other question before we move on?
Did I read the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying they has
to be written
and they have to accept it? Yeah, there's a little bit of
ambiguity at the conclusion of this גמרא, Gemara, whether he is, the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma might be saying both. And then, then it
makes more sense of the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. That is true.
So there's a little ambiguity whether whether in the end the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma is saying it's only that it's written or that
you need both written and מחזיק. machzik. If you need both, then
at least you can understand that yes, they do the fact-finding and
they need to be doubly sure and use this other criteria. Yes.
So thank you, that is a possibility in the תנא קמא. Tanna
Kamma. Okay, so let's go on now. גופא. Gufa. So now, so
now we're done with exploring the issue of Samaritans and what are
the things that they may or may not be careful in. We're
going to go look at the other interesting discussion about the non-observant
Jew or the non-שומר כשרות shomer kashrut Jew. אמר רבא ישראל מומר
אוכל נבילות לתיאבון. Amar Rava Yisrael mumar ochel nevelot l'teiavon. So a
ישראל Yisrael who is rebellious, not really rebellious for spite, but he's
non-observant in a certain area and eats non-kosher meat, specifically נבילות nevelot
here because it means non-שחט shechted meat, which is exactly relevant, exactly
what we care about, that if he שחט shechted correctly, he doesn't
care about, he's prepared to eat non-שחט shechted meat לתיאבון l'teiavon for
appetite, for desire, not in spite, not in any ideological reason, but
just because it's not important enough for him and if he can
save a few dollars a pound or if it, if for some
reason he, it tastes better, he's going to eat the נבילה. nevela.
Okay. בודק סכין ונותן לו Bodek sakin v'noten lo in that case,
you can check the knife and give the knife to him. ומותר
לאכול משחיטתו u'muttar l'echol mishchitatu you can eat his שחיטה shechita you
don't even have to observe him as long as you give him
a pre-checked knife. מאי טעמא Mai taama what's the reason says the
גמרא? Gemara? כיון דאיכא היתר ואיסורא Keivan d'ika heter v'issura since he
can either, it's equal, you know, it's equal possibilities, he can either
eat kosher meat or non-kosher meat here, meaning it's all going to
determine how he שחט. shechts. So given that those are equal, you
know, all other things being equal, לא שבק היתירא ואכיל איסורא lo
shavek heiteira v'achil issura we will assume he's not going to abandon
the היתר heter for the איסור. issur. He'll pick the איסור issur
if there's any, if there's any incentive, if it's cheaper, if it
tastes better, but if you have two identical pieces of meat and
there's no reason to pick the איסור, issur, he then, all things
being equal, he'd rather eat the היתר. heter. So therefore if you
check the knife, so he has no effort he has to expend
to make kosher meat, he's going to have to slaughter it either
way, there's presumably no harder to slaughter it correctly than incorrectly, so
we'll assume he slaughters it correctly. Let me just read one more
sentence. אי הכי I hachi says the גמרא Gemara if that's true
כי לא בדיק נמי ki lo badik nami if you haven't checked
the knife, let's assume he'll try to eat kosher rather than non-kosher.
No, מטרח לא טרח mitrach lo tarach
he's not going to go to the effort to check the knife,
to sharpen the knife, to get a good knife, so any little
reason he he doesn't care and he'll eat the טריפה. treif. But
if there's no reason, then he's going to choose the kosher. So
therefore he'll choose to do it correctly if it requires no particular
effort.
Yes, so there's five other things that are in the...
so that's what I said before, you would think that the effort
to be careful about how you're doing it is a serious effort
and why should I be careful? But I think what you have
to say, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't say this is, presumably he
knows how to do it correctly, right? Or else we wouldn't be...
that goes to the previous discussion about מוחזק muchzak and whatever. So
if you know how to do it, you know, then it's almost
like it's almost like rote, like it's almost like muscle memory, it's
like almost in some ways easier to do it correctly than incorrectly.
Okay, now the question though could be is that sometimes a problem
occurs, you're not, you know, you've done it correctly but it got
it got caught on something or the knife got a got a
nick or something, you know. But it's interesting, we're not saying he's
like the כותי, Kuti, we're not saying that he's going to try
to mess us up, but you know, but on the other hand,
if we believe his reporting, then why do I have to be
בודק הסכין bodek hasakin why not just believe his reporting? So it
sounds like we don't believe his reporting. So then the real question
I would ask is not is not the care that's required to
to do the act correctly because that is being assumed to be
once you know how to do it, no more effort than doing
it incorrectly, but I would more be concerned about how do we
know an accidental problem didn't come up,
which you need עדים edim או o גברא gavra over.
Right, I understand that's the חידוש. chiddush. Here you got a guy,
here you got a guy that doesn't care about eating non-kosher meat
and if you set up the circumstances you don't have to observe
him. Right? So my bigger problem is not the effort to do
it correctly because I can imagine that once you know what you're
doing there's no greater effort. My bigger problem is how do you
know that some problem didn't come up by accident that he's not
bothered to report? I don't know, unless we're assuming that we're not
going to assume accident, you know, some type of accident if the
setting is correct. It's like חזקה chazakah that everything is correct.
And if he's
not going to lie about it? What? Well, if he's not going
to lie, then why do you need בודק סכין? bodek sakin? Even
without בודק סכין, bodek sakin, why don't you just ask him after
the fact, did you, you know, did you check your knife correctly?
So... what?
Okay, so it sounds like we're not going to trust his reporting.
Okay, so now let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. So, אמר
ליה רבנן לרבא. amar leih rabbanan l'Rava. So the rabbis said to
רבא, Rava, תניא דמסייע לך. tanya d'mesayeia lach. I will bring you...
so rabbis should probably mean the rabbinical students. They said to רבא,
Rava, I will bring you a ברייתא braita that supports your position.
חמצן של עובדי עבירה אחר הפסח. chamtzan shel ovdei aveirah achar haPesach.
חמץ chametz after פסח Pesach of people, Jews that actually kept חמץ
chametz in their house over פסח. Pesach. So, now there's a problem
about חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח. chametz she'avar alav haPesach. Can you eat
it? It was חמץ chametz that was held by a Jew over
פסח. Pesach. So the ברייתא braita says, מותר. mutar. You actually are
allowed after פסח Pesach to eat their חמץ. chametz. Why? It's חמץ
שעבר עליו הפסח. chametz she'avar alav haPesach.
מפני שהן מחליפין, mipnei shehein machlifin, because
since, why did they keep the חמץ chametz after over פסח? Pesach?
You know, cause they're too committed to חמץ, chametz, they're not willing
to give it up for פסח. Pesach. But after פסח, Pesach, then
they will... they'll try to make it better, halachically better. So what
they'll do is they'll go to the next door neighbor Jew and
they'll swap their חמץ chametz for his חמץ. chametz. Because now at
least if it's after פסח, Pesach, might as well eat חמץ chametz
that was not over... עליו הפסח alav haPesach rather than eating חמץ
שעבר עליו הפסח. chametz she'avar alav haPesach. So again, think about this
mentality. It's crazy, right? I'll eat חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach where
it's כרת, kares, but after פסח Pesach where it's probably only a
דרבנן d'rabbanan or it's certainly not a חיוב כרת, chiyuv kares, but
since there there's no loss to me to keep to be more...
to be a little פרום, frum, so there I will swap it
with a non-Jew so I can eat the kosher חמץ chametz and
not the טריף tref חמץ. chametz. Okay, so again, what I think
is amazing is either that this was actually the mentality of people,
that you know, this was a phenomenon at that time that people
would make these חשבונות. cheshbonos. And the other thing is that the
חז"ל Chazal were willing, you know, to actually take people that ממש
mamash violated כשרות kashrus and חמץ chametz and פסח Pesach and still
say under these circumstances we can trust that it's okay.
But how is that different from people who don't observe שבת Shabbos
or go to יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
Oh well, that's different. That's like because there יום כיפור Yom Kippur
is like weightier and it's one day out of the year. I
mean, here it's like ממש mamash you've been eating חמץ chametz the
whole פסח Pesach which is a חיוב כרת, chiyuv kares, you know,
but come after פסח Pesach you're going to go swap it with
your friend in order so you're no longer doing the איסור issur
of חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח. chametz she'avar alav haPesach. Okay.
I think it goes better with what you were saying before about
the כותים. Kusim. Yeah, that it doesn't... it doesn't say if they
swap. Right. It says we can presume.
We can presume and the גמרא Gemara is going to make the
דיוק diyuk in a second, right.
Okay, and it's... it seems like a even more clear than the
case of the כותי, Kusi, a way that the rabbis can
avoid segregation of community.
Right. So that's an interesting question here as well, which is are
we going to make these assumptions not necessarily because we know they're
factually correct? I mean, not that let's assume we don't know that
they're factually incorrect, but we don't know that they're factually correct, but
it allows us more to not exclude people. Right. So that is
an interesting question as well. How much does that factor into the
חשבון? cheshbon? Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So
you see that we're going to assume that somebody who in a
certain way is not observant, if it's not any loss to them,
they'll try to be observant. So סברוה, savruha, we assumed, הא מני
רבי יהודה היא, ha mani Rabbi Yehuda hi, this is רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר חמץ אחר הפסח דאורייתא, d'amar chametz achar haPesach d'oraisa,
that it's even biblical not to eat חמץ אחר הפסח. chametz achar
haPesach. And we can trust them even on a biblical matter. וקתני
מפני שהן מחליפין, v'katani mipnei shehein machlifin,
because they swap their חמץ. chametz. אלמא, alma, we see, לא שבק
היתירא ואכיל איסורא, lo shavik heteira v'achil issura, that even when it
comes to trusting them for a biblical matter like here we're doing
שחיטה, shechitah, there we're doing חמץ אחר הפסח, chametz achar haPesach, we
can assume that they do not abandon היתר heter for the sake
of איסור, issur, all other things being equal. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ממאי? mimai? How do you know that it's רבי יהודה? Rabbi
Yehuda? דילמא רבי שמעון היא? dilma Rabbi Shimon hi? Maybe it's רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דאמר חמץ אחר הפסח דרבנן, d'amar chametz achar haPesach
d'rabbanan, that the whole prohibition after פסח, Pesach, this is the way
we rule, is only rabbinic. So therefore why would that change it?
Because maybe that's why we'll trust them because it's only a rabbinic
issue.
וכי מקלינן... v'chi maklinan... we can...
no no no, it's not what they'll do, it's what we'll assume.
Let's finish it. וכי מקלינן בדרבנן, v'chi maklinan b'd'rabbanan,
when will we buy into this assumption that they're going to do
it the right way? Maybe they won't do it the right way,
but we'll allow ourselves to assume that for rabbinic matters where the
consequence is not as great. בדאורייתא, b'd'oraisa, but for biblical matters like
kosher meat, לא מקלינן, lo maklinan, we're not going to presume that
they're doing things the right way. So the גמרא Gemara says, no
no no. ואי נמי רבי שמעון, v'ee nami Rabbi Shimon, even if
it is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that it's only a rabbinic concern,
מי קתני? mi katani? שאני אומר החליפו? she'ani omer hechlifu? The ברייתא
braita doesn't say because I can... I can... I can suspect... I
can presume that they switched, which means in all honesty I really
don't know. But I'm going to make the assumption even though I
don't really know it's true. That would be שאני אומר. shani omer.
So if it was that we really don't know but we're going
to allow ourselves to assume it for rabbinic issues, it would have
said שאני אומר. shani omer. I don't know, but I'm going to
assume it. Okay, but it doesn't say that. בפני שמחליפין תני. Bipnei
shemachlifin tani. It says because they swap, which means that I'm going
to assume that I do know, meaning I'm going to assert that
I really do know that they swap. So now we're going to...
what, it's not like I don't know but I'll make a convenient
assumption. At least I'm going to say that I actually do know.
So ודאי מחליפין, vadai machlifin, so that they definitely swap. And now
I'm going to say ומה בדרבנן לא שבקי היתירא ואכלי איסורא. uma
biderabbanan lo shabki heiteira ve'achli issura. Now the argument comes even stronger.
If even for a rabbinic matter they're going to go out of
their way to make sure that they do it better if it's
no loss to them, so בדאורייתא לא כל שכן? bedioraita lo kol
sheken? How much more so for a biblical matter? If it's no
effort and no loss to them, will they go out of their
way to make sure they do it correctly? So the גמרא Gemara
thinks that we have an issue here, right? And goes back also
to the point that David was making. Are we really saying in
all honesty we don't know, but this is something that we're going
to assume? So the גמרא Gemara says if that were what it
was saying, it would have used the phrase שאני אומר. shani omer.
So at least we're not saying that that's what we're doing. Whether
we are still doing that or not is a big question, but
at least we're not saying that that's what we're doing. We're saying
that we know for a fact that they actually do it. And
if they're going to go to that effort even for something rabbinic,
certainly they'll go for that for דאורייתא, dioraita, all things being equal,
they're going to make it less halakhically problematic.
Under either meaning, we don't need to confirm the fact.
Right, right. It's just in one we're saying we don't know and
we're assuming, and the other we're saying we do know. But in
neither are we actually going and investigating the matter. That's absolutely correct.
Is that true for the second case though? We just have a
different state of mind.
What do you mean?
That we're saying we do know. We need to have some evidence.
No, no, no, that's what David just said. We're just saying, look,
רבא, Rava, here's your position. We are going to always assume that
we know for sure that this person that doesn't care about it
will always go for the היתר heiter if it's no effort to
him and it's no loss to him. The נפקא מינה nafka mina
is that you can trust it even on a biblical matter because
we're saying that we know it, we're going to assume it as
a fact.
But just very, very basically, these seem to be very different economic
transactions. The case of שחיטה, shechita, people... I assume that people didn't
שחט shacht their own animals. They took them to somebody who was
an expert and in business. Yes, there was a business of being
a שוחט. shochet.
Certainly for large animals, birds may be a little bit more common.
But okay, in the second case, the case of מצה, matzah, we
know from שו״תים shutim that מצה matzah was baked in the home.
Industrial מצה matzah production or trading in מצה matzah actually only developed
in the nineteenth century. And this case of trading in grain, because
that's really what this guy is doing... I'm sorry, person, man or
woman, is doing.
Well, it might just be inviting you over for a meal, but
okay.
But if he's swapping out his grain with somebody else, it feels
like we're talking about significant quantity.
That could be, that's interesting.
The impact of this is actually that that person is actually going
to be forced to be in business and transactions with the non-Jewish
community unless you evaluate it this way. So some require... the first
two are questions of agency, where you're hiring somebody to do something
you otherwise do yourself. And the third question is a question of
what is the eventual economics of the community going to be? Are
you going to say we can only deal in certain commodities with
people who we know to be reliable, whether or not they're our
agents?
I understand your problems. Why would you not say מחליפין machlifin is
you go to your neighbor and say, 'Hey, I want to get
rid of my...'?
Oh no, no, your neighbor Jew would never swap it. Non-neighbor, non-Jew.
No, but David is saying that when we're talking now to the
whole Jewish community, we're saying after פסח, Pesach, you have to buy
from non-Jews? Or can you actually do all your חמץ chametz purchasing
from Jews, either because Jews were... kept פסח Pesach and did all
their baking after פסח, Pesach, or even if they didn't, we're going
to work with this assumption that they swapped it out? And you
can do all of your purchasing after פסח Pesach amongst Jews and
you don't have to go to non-Jews to do it.
Or as a communal...
right. Okay, the only way we're doing it is by assuming that
this one guy did go to non-Jews, but at least as a
communal thing, we're not saying that that's how you have to do
your transactions. Right, that's interesting to think of it through that lens.
Okay, so let's now see where the גמרא Gemara goes from this.
Okay, לימא מסייע ליה, leima mesayei lei,
let's try to bring another proof. הכל שוחטין, Hakol shochtin, so here's
a תוספתא Tosefta that actually seems to be a commentary on our
משנה Mishna about what is הכל. hakol. So it's actually interesting, and
that's a little exercise at home for the reader to look at
this תוספתא, Tosefta, and I'm serious, because the whole different reads we
had in our גמרא Gemara about what הכל hakol comes to include
seem like they were takeoff on this תוספתא. Tosefta. And even the
תוספתא Tosefta the way it's quoted here is not the way it
appears in full. So for those that are interested in looking at
that. But let's see where it's quoted. הכל שוחטין, Hakol shochtin, all
can shecht, ואפילו כותי, ve'afilu Kuti, ואפילו ערל, ve'afilu arel, ואפילו ישראל
מומר. ve'afilu Yisrael mumar. So there are two of the reads that
we just had earlier in the גמרא, Gemara, the כותי Kuti and
the ישראל מומר, Yisrael mumar, and what it throws in is the
uncircumcised Jew. So האי ערל היכי דמי, hai arel heichi dami, what
is the case of this uncircumcised Jew? אילימא מתו אחיו מחמת מילה,
ilima meisu achav machamat milah, if it's somebody that has a good
reason to be uncircumcised, his brothers died during the act of circumcision,
which means basically he's a family of hemophiliacs. So therefore he has
a right not to be circumcised. So האי ישראל מעליא הוא, Hai
Yisrael maya hu, he's a totally good Jew, there's no different halachic
status. אלא פשיטא, Ella peshita, must be talking מומר לערלות mumar l'areilus
that he is a mumer for that he rejects circumcision, maybe it
started with his father rejecting it, but now that he's an adult
he rejects it as well.
Okay, so וכסבר, ve-kasavar, interesting in the contemporary context about a dispute
going around right now in San Francisco. Anyway, וכסבר, ve-kasavar, מומר לדבר
אחד לא הוי מומר לכל התורה כולה, mumar l'davar echad lo havei
mumar l'chol ha-Torah kullah, and what it's assuming is just because you
reject one area of הלכה halacha doesn't impact your status in another
area of הלכה. halacha. This is very important that the גמרא Gemara
really understands that when we pasken this people's psychology. So for example,
what's challenging about our case is the guy is not observing כשרות
Kashrus of meat, but normally the גמרא Gemara we assume that even
if somebody is not good about one area, even a more severe
area, we can trust him in another. So for example, let's say
you have a guy that's a known adulterer. Okay, you can nevertheless
trust him as a משגיח Mashgiach or as a שוחט, Shochet, technically
in הלכה, halacha, because people will compartmentalize. That's an area which I
don't do, this is an area that I do do, even if
that area is more strict halachically than this area. מומר לדבר אחד
או חשוד על דבר אחד Mumar l'davar echad o chashud al davar
echad is not חשוד על דבר אחר chashud al davar acher as
long as they're
conceived as of separate categories. So that's a question about חשוד chashud
about trustworthiness in one area and another way, and here it's about
מומר, mumar, does it affect your status? Do we see you as
like out of the פרשה parshah for these areas? So for ערלות,
areilus, the גמרא Gemara is interpreting this to mean that even though
you're rejecting ברית מילה, Bris Milah, which might even be seen as
like something that represents כל התורה כולה, kol ha-Torah kullah, but nevertheless
we say that's one area and that does not affect your status
when it comes to issues of כשרות. Kashrus.
Even לכתחילה, lechatchila, yeah, הכל שוחטין.
Hakol Shochtin. Okay, and so let's finish this thought. That's what we
learned from ערל, arel, that just because you've rejected one area of
הלכה halacha does not affect your status in another. Now we say,
אימא סיפא, eima seifa,
let's look at the end. ואפילו ישראל מומר, va'afilu Yisrael mumar, and
you can even trust the שחיטה shechita of a ישראל Yisrael who
has rejected something. האי מומר היכי דמי, Hai mumar heichi dami, what's
the case of a מומר? mumar? אילימא לדבר אחר, Ilima l'davar acher,
if it's a מומר mumar that you've rejected some unrelated area, like
you've rejected you know whatever שבת, Shabbos, well שבת Shabbos we'll get
to, but something else, so האי היינו מומר לערלות, hai hainu mumar
l'areilus,
that's just like ערלות, areilus, that just because you reject one area
doesn't affect your status in כשרות. Kashrus. אלא לאו, Ella lav, so
what we must be talking about to add a new case is
מומר לאותו דבר, mumar l'oso davar, that you've actually rejected כשרות, Kashrus,
right? That's the next stage, that you actually don't eat kosher-shechted meat.
וכדרבא, ve-ki-d'Rava, and this is like רבא. Rava. So he says, look
רבא, Rava, this is your case. It says a מומר mumar you
can trust their שחיטה shechita and because we've already mentioned ערלות, areilus,
it must mean somebody that has actually doesn't keep kosher meat, and
nevertheless we can trust their שחיטה. shechita. That's a support for you.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. לא, Lo, not necessarily.
לעולם אימא לך מומר לאותו דבר לא. Le'olam eima lach mumar l'oso
davar lo. I will tell you that if you've actually rejected כשרות,
Kashrus, even if it's just out of desire or appetite, we can't
trust you for shechting. And now it becomes very interesting. מאי טעמא,
Mai ta'ama, since רבא's Rava logic was all things being equal you'd
rather do the היתר heter than the איסור, issur, גמרא Gemara says
it's not so obvious. כיון דדש ביה כהיתרא דמי ליה. Keivan d'dash
bei k'heteira dami leh.
Once you have trampled on it, it's now it's like a היתר,
heter, meaning you're assuming, the גמרא Gemara says to רבא Rava and
you really understand this psychology better than רבא, Rava, you're assuming that
the guy in his mind is still saying, I'm doing an איסור
issur but I'm doing it because I have a reason to. But
when I don't have a reason I'll rather do the היתר. heter.
And he's still keeping in his mind categories of איסור issur and
היתר. heter. גמרא Gemara says that's not what happens. If you've constantly
been eating non-shechted meat because you save a few dollars a pound,
after a while you no longer consider it איסור, issur, it becomes
like היתר. heter. So for you why should I bother doing the
היתר heter over the איסור? issur? I don't consider this I no
longer consider this איסור issur anyway. So it makes a lot of
sense and in another גמרא Gemara says this says this in another
time not in this context it says עבירה דאדם עובר בה ושונה,
aveirah d'adam over bah v'shonah, anything עבירה aveirah that a person has
done twice, נעשית לו כהיתר. na'aseis lo k'heter. It all it now
it's no longer an איסור. issur. It's becomes like a היתר heter
in your mind, it's not even doing anything wrong. And רב ישראל
סלנטר Rav Yisrael Salanter said a beautiful coda to that and he
says and if you do it three times it's like a
מצוה. mitzvah. We so much rationalize what we're doing. So anyway, okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says we may totally reject רבא. Rava. We
say that even all things being equal you're going to keep on
eating doing your איסור issur because you no longer even recognize those
categories. So how do we read the ברייתא? Baraisa?
So אלא מומר לעבודת כוכבים, Ella mumar l'avodas kochavim, just to finish
this thought, אלא מומר לעבודת כוכבים. Ella mumar l'avodas kochavim. So what
does it mean that you can trust a מומר? mumar? Even if
a guy is עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah. וכדרב ענני, ve-ki-d'Rav
Anani, like רב ענני, Rav Anani, דאמר רב ענני אמר שמואל, d'amar
Rav Anani amar Shmuel, ישראל מומר לעבודת כוכבים מותר. Yisrael mumar l'avodas
kochavim mutar.
Now think of this, we're
finding out some amazing possibilities in the תוספות, Tosafot, right? First we
have רבא Rava that says that you can trust a guy's שחיטה
shechita who doesn't keep כשרות, kashrut, and then now we see that
a guy who's עובד עבודה זרה, oved avoda zara, who worships idols,
you can—and interestingly, it's saying you can't trust the שחיטה shechita of
a guy that doesn't keep כשרות kashrut because then he obviously doesn't
care about כשרות, kashrut, but if he doesn't care about other things,
even if he's an עובד עבודה זרה, oved avoda zara, okay, just
because I'm an עובד עבודה זרה oved avoda zara doesn't mean I
don't keep a kosher home. So therefore, you can trust this guy's
שחיטה. shechita. So we will continue with this tomorrow; as I said,
this is where we really get into fascinating discussions about status and
trustworthiness and ways that, you know, go against our normal assumptions. To
be continued tomorrow.